the web that we all use the Web 2.0 is
going through a revolution the way users
interact with it and the way we as
developers build for it is changing
radically we need to change the way we
think about websites and how we make
them we need to update the mental models
from Web 2.0 and replace them with new
ones this revolution this new way of
building applications for the web is
called Web tree
Nicholas in and welcome to a new video
If you like this kind of blockchain
content and you want to see more then
please consider leaving a like and
subscribing to the channel let's get
started to understand web3 we have to
talk about Web 2.0 and for that let's
first talk about web 1.0 web 1.0 was
when the internet started when there
were no web designers when websites were
kind of ugly and full of gifs this is
how Amazon looked like in 1995. this is
Disney in 1996. this is Apple in 1997
and this is Coca-Cola's website in 1999.
yuck with web 1.0 if you wanted to put
your content on the internet you could
but you had to know how to make a
website and set up a server and all that
the content on the web 1.0 was mostly
static where users were only the
consumers of data this was also in part
because from a developer's point of view
web sites could not do that much the
browsers and languages like JavaScript
and CSS were not powerful enough making
a website do cool stuff or at least
making it look beautiful was incredibly
hard to give you an example of how bad
it was if today you have a rectangle and
you want to give a round corners to it
all you have to do is write one line of
code border radius and it will be done
that simple thing was not even possible
before we had to create four images of
the four corners and we had to manually
position each one of them crazy after
web 1.0 came what we now live on and
that is Web 2.0 Web 2.0 is when the rise
of social media happens where instead of
static websites user generated content
takes the center stage before the users
were the consumers of data with Web 2.0
they became the producers of that data
Web 2.0 created all this social media
Giants that we have today and that was
helped by the fact that we now have what
people from the 90s would have
considered a super computer in our
pocket the thing that happened with user
generated content is that it all ended
up flowing to the same website we're in
the web 1.0 you found a website that you
like because somebody told you about it
and you had to put it in your bookmark
so you don't forget in the Web 2.0 you
don't visit that many websites and you
know where to go to depending on the
type of the content photos Instagram
videos YouTube short video Tick Tock
short text and opinions Twitter bragging
about your career LinkedIn this is what
we can describe as centralization all
this data created by us it's all going
to the same places stored in databases
that we have no access to having all
these massive amounts of data made these
companies very rich they learned that
they can use the data you create to sell
you things or sell the data itself as a
product apart from benefiting
disproportionately from other people's
data another thing that Web 2.0 did for
social media companies is that it gave
them power over the public this course
if they decide they want to censor you
they will if they decide that what you
are saying should not be heard they will
turn you off companies careers debates
news discussion they are all developing
inside of platforms that we have no
control over these companies are being
used as public goods but they aren't
public goods on Web 2.0 you have to
trust you have to trust that the
companies that have your data won't do
anything bad with it and that they will
respect your privacy even though if you
programmed a back-end server before you
know how trivial it is to build an admin
panel and see all the records on a
database you also have to trust and hope
that these companies won't censor you or
quietly modify the algorithm to make you
change your opinion on things now here
is when web3 comes in Dr Gavin wood the
co-founder of ethereum and the creator
of polkadot and kusama was the first to
come up with the word web Tree on his
own words web3 is the service without
the service provider using things like
blockchains a smart contracts
cryptography peer-to-peer networks among
many other things we can replace the
infrastructure of Twitter Instagram
Facebook and YouTube we can remove the
middleman and create applications that
are not controlled by a single entity
applications where the users own and
control the data they produce
applications where you don't have to
trust trust less applications that you
can verify and audit anytime you like
these applications will be decentralized
which means they will not be hosted in
one single server controlled by one
single party they will be stored in a
network of computers they will be
replicated across the network making
them censorship resistant web 3 apps
should not feel different than Web 2.0
apps from the user point of view the
difference will be on the infrastructure
on the back end of the services almost
every piece of how a web service is made
apart from the UI will be replaced by a
public open source and decentralized
solution instead of using a database
your website will store its data on a
blockchain instead of writing your
backing code thinking is going to run in
a server hosted on AWS you will instead
write a smart contract that will be
stored on a blockchain and executed by a
decentralized virtual machine instead of
having user accounts your users will
have a wallet and they will own their
identity in their security instead of
storing static files the JS and the CSS
or netlify or virtual and instead of
storing user uploads in AWS S3 you will
use interplanetary file system or airwav
instead of using third-party apis to get
external data like like Market data
Sports data weather data news data
whatever you will use oracles like chain
link or flux those projects which I am
not telling you to invest on by the way
are just a small part of all the
projects that are being built to be the
building blocks of the infrastructure
required to build a web that is more
open and transparent this does not mean
that web3 does not have its detractors
some people say that web3 is total BS
and even Elon Musk says that it seems
more like a marketing buzzword than a
reality right now and I agree with this
today it is used mostly as a buzzword by
companies that think they can sprinkle a
little bit of web3 and blockchain along
with a little bit of metaverse to look
cool the truth is that it is hard to
predict what kind of services will be
born with web 3 infrastructure not
because it is useless but because it is
too new what we can do today with web 3
is not something we thought it was real
we have been thinking with Web 2.0
mental models for too long we can't even
imagine the things that will be built
because they just weren't possible to
build before in 1943 the chairman of IBM
said and I quote I think there is a
World Market for maybe five computers
end quote in 1995 the creator of the
ethernet set quote I predict the
internet will soon go spectacularly
Supernova and in 1996 catastrophically
collapse now I don't think they said
this because they were idiots I think
that with the information they had at
the time in the context of a world in
1943 computers actually looked useless
in the context of 1995 the internet
might have seemed like a buzzword as
well companies and governments were
working well without it if you asked me
in 1995 what companies would benefit the
most from the Internet or what can be
built using the inter internet I would
have not been able to predict over or
Netflix when the internet came what
happened was not that they already
existing companies just migrated to it
and became more productive it wasn't
that bakeries and hair salons just got a
website and we just kept going what
happened was that apart from killing
certain companies the internet created
its own companies it made possible
companies that were not possible before
Amazon Google Twitter Facebook some of
the most valuable companies on the
planet are not possible without the
internet itself they don't make sense in
a world without internet Larry and
Sergey from Google didn't come up with
idea of a search engine before the
internet existed and we're just waiting
anxiously for it it was when the
internet arrived that they saw its
potential and started building Bezos
wasn't also waiting for the internet to
get started building Amazon when the
internet came he saw the potential and
the opportunity I personally think that
it will be the same with web 3. the
services and apps that are being built
on web3 will not make sense in a world
without web3 just like Google doesn't
make sense in a world without the
internet and that is the end of this
video thank you for watching if you ever
felt curious about the meaning of web 3
I hope that you found the explanation on
this video useful if you like this kind
of content and you would like to see
more then please consider leaving a like
and subscribing to the channel it really
really helps thank you see you on the
next video and please let me know in the
comments if there is any other
blockchain related word that you are
curious about I am making some sort of a
blockchain dictionary and I am looking
for words to put on it and don't forget
if you want to learn to code and you
want to do it for free with me click on
the link below and I will see you there
stay free be happy see you in the next
one bye